Finding Aid for Michigan School Health Association records, 1933-1991
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Michigan School Health Association records 1933-1991
Michigan School Health Association.
4 linear feet
85288 Bf 2
Organization concerned with school health programs and education. Records include constitution, board minutes, committee files, history of the organization, activities files, correspondence, publications, and photographs.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was deposited by the Association (Donor No. 6180 ) in 1978 and 1984.
Periodic additions to the records expected.
The collection is open to research.
The Michigan School Health Association (MSHA) was established in 1933 to bring together professionals engaged in school health work. Originally called the Michigan Association of School Physicians, its name was changed to MSHA in 1936.
The goals of the organization are several. One is to promote comprehensive and constructive school health programs for Michigan's school children. A second objective is to develop and maintain a body of concerned professionals and lay people devoted to fostering mutual cooperation between school personnel and those other persons and agencies waning to improve the social, physical and emotional health of children and youth. In addition, the MSHA endeavors to represent the people of Michigan with its participation in the American School Health Association.
The MSHA works to achieve its goals through a variety of activities. These include annual and special state-wide meetings, conferences and workshops and the publication of newsletters.
The records of the MSHA consist of five series: Histories, Organizational Material (1933-1983), Correspondence and Memoranda (1934-1982), Activities (1935-1983), and Publications.
Subjects:
Public health--Michigan.; Schools--Michigan.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Anniversaries.; Banquets.; Exhibitions.; Michigan School Health Association.
Contributors:
corpname; persname; geogname
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Histories
  - Histories (Box 1)
- Organizational Material
  Organizational Material (1933-1983) contains minutes and other records dating from the early years of the organization to the present. The committee files primarily document the late 19701s.
  - Constitution and Bylaws, 1933-1982 (Box 1)
  - Minutes, 1933-1982, 4 folders (Box 1)
  - Financial Reports, 1934-1983 (scattered dates) (Box 1)
  - Membership Lists, 1943-1982 (scattered dates) (Box 1)
  - Committees
    - Archives, 1976-1984 (Box 1)
    - Awards, 1975-1982 (Box 1)
    - Membership, 1975-1981 (Box 1)
    - Nominating, 1975 (Box 1)
    - Program, 1934-1981 (scattered dates) (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
- Correspondence and Memoranda
  Correspondence and Memoranda (1934-1982) includes incoming and out-going correspondence from members and other people involved in organizations which worked closely with MSHA (e.g., the Michigan Health Council). There is a gap in this series for the years 1952-1956.
  - 1934-1957 P folders) (Box 1)
  - 1958-1982, 6 folders (Box 1)
- Activities, 1935-1983
  Activities (1935-1983) documents primarily events which took place in the early 1980's. One such activity was the School Health Education Resource Coordination Project which was a joint effort between MSHA and the Michigan Health Council to coordinate, codify and disseminate school health resources.
  - Conferences and Workshops
    - Annual Conferences, 1935-1959 (scattered dates) (Box 2)
    - "Instruction in the 80s" (Department of Education), 1982 (Box 2)
    - Leadership Workshop, 1957-1962 (scattered dates) (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
  - Fiftieth Anniversary, 1983 (including commemorative Resolution) (Box 2)
  - Grant Proposal, 1982 (Box 2)
  - Liaison, Group (MSHA and Department of Education), 1981 (Box 2)
  - Project Health, 1980-1981 (Box 2)
  - School Aged Health Network, 1980-1981 (Box 2)
  - School Health Education Resources Coordination Proje ct, 1982-1983, 2 folders (Box 2)
- Publications
  Publications consists of newsletters, pamphlets and other publications of MSHA.
  - Newsletters, 1943-1983 (scattered dates) (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
- Photographs
  The Photographs series includes prints of 50th anniversary awards luncheon and other conferences.
  - Photos (Box 2)
- Records, September 1983-1991
  - September 1983-August 1989 (Box 2)
    (November 1984 acession)
  - 1983/84-1984/85 (Box 3)
  - 1986-1991 (Box 4)